Hello and welcome back to
another video with it's Dr. Dan.
And today we're gonna be learning
how to name ethers and we're gonna
go over both the IUPAC and the
common naming systems for how to
name the specific functional group.
So just as a reminder, what ethers are,
so they consist of functional group
that has an oxygen atom that's attached
by single bonds to two carbon groups.
That are both, or aromatics.
So essentially you always kind of see
the little O holding hands with these
two little R groups on both sides.
So it's like, it's kinda like
swinging between the two.
So I like to think of the oxygen
as like a little child holding
hands with its two parents as it's
swinging hands, um, with both parts.
So, um, essentially with this oxygen,
just like, uh, alcohols as well,
it has that bent geometry to it.
You know, it has those four
groups, those two lone pairs.
So we're gonna go through and learn
about how to name them really quick
and do a bunch of practice problems.
So let's see if we can figure
it out together, and thank
you so much for watching.
Let's go take a look.
The first thing is, is that it's three
simple steps for how to name Ether and
the IUPAC naming system, which is the
official naming system that we use.
Internationally.
So with this system, what you're
gonna do first is you're gonna
first name the longest carbon chain.
So I have an ether up here,
uh, that we're gonna be naming.
So when we're going to go through this,
so we gotta find, look at the two branches
that are on each side of the ether.
So you can see on the left hand
side of this little molecule here
that I have two carbons on the left.
And on the right I have a total of four.
So what are we gonna do?
We're gonna name the one on the left hand
side here, so as you can see, 1, 2, 3, 4.
What is that gonna be?
You're gonna have the butane.
Okay.
So the next step, it says,
name the oxygen and the smaller
alkyl  group as an alkoxy group.
Right.
So what does that mean?
It's combining the Oxy prefix for the
Ether and whatever the alkane  name is.
So in this case, right, we're gonna
kind of do the same thing we see.
Okay?
We're gonna be naming the
specific side that's on the left.
So it's two carbons, right?
So the F is gonna be the portion
that's referring to the Alcan, and
then we're gonna end that with Oxy.
So it's gonna be eth, Oxy is gonna
be the beginning of the name.
So what we're gonna now do is we're gonna
combine both those different pieces.
So we'll take our oxy, right?
We're gonna copy that, and
then we'll bring in our butane.
So what does that make?
The name now is Oxy Butane, right?
So you're kind of naming it just like
a normal alkin chain, and you're saying
that, Hey, I got this little branch
that's attached to it, essentially.
And that's generally the way
to, to really look at it.
Now the final step depends whether
or not you have, uh, any kind of,
let's say if they're not attached
exactly at carbon number one.
So maybe you might have like the
Ether deposition, two or three
or somewhere as a general branch.
So what you're gonna do is, in this case,
you gotta number your longer carbon.
And what you're gonna do is
you're gonna number actually
starting close to the ether.
So being that this one, the longest
chain is only the part in green here.
So the one on the right, uh, you have to
start numbering it starting next to it.
So in this situation, what would
the official name of this be?
Would be?
One oxy butane would be the entire.
Now keep in mind, you know, we
usually do drop ones whenever
it's at the end of a chain.
But if you wanna be thorough about
it and just make sure, Hey, I know
this really well, I would recommend
numbering it, but let's do a bunch
of practice prompts together.
Let's see how you do with them.
So, as I kind of say all the time with
these, if you'd like to, I'd recommend you
pause the video as you see the examples.
Try to do it on your own.
And if you get stuck, then you
can, like, then you can take
a look at how I explain it.
Or if you're like, oh, this is
easy, you can fast forward a
little bit, go to the next part.
Right?
So that's where all the chapter
labels down below are for.
All right, let's take
a look at the examples.
Okay.
The very first one.
So we're gonna go through
the same exact tricks.
So step one was, right, we name
our longest, uh, carbon chain.
So in this case you have two.
So we're gonna have ethane.
Then we're gonna name our Alcock
group, so our oxy portion.
So that's, oh, that's this part
on the, on the left hand side.
Right?
So we have one that's there.
So this is gonna be meth and then oxy.
And being that as before, we can see
that it's at the end of the chain.
So it's gonna be one methoxy pain.
Okay?
Now for this one, we have some
special, special parts here.
So we have the cyclo  alkane
that's here on the left hand side.
So this is gonna be a very special part.
So generally these are what's
gonna be your parent chain for
all these different, uh, ethers.
So this will be cyclo butane.
And then for our shorter part, right, we
have the two carbons here on the left,
and they're also connected to position
number one as well on our cyclo group.
So this is gonna be one oxy.
Cyclo butane.
So that's gonna be the entire name.
Now, if we go to the
next one, same idea here.
All right, so we can also
name aromatic groups too.
So what are we gonna name
our big ring structure?
Well, that's gonna be benzene, right?
So being that we have that, the aromatic
shape and then the other portion, right?
So naming the alkoxy group.
Well, for this one, well,
how are you gonna name it?
You have this unique shape here.
So this is one of your, your fancy
propole, different shapes, right?
Um, so this one will be
iso propoxy benzene, right?
So you can also combine it with the
iso sac and turt shapes as well.
Okay.
Now this last one, so once
again, we have our longest chain.
So we see we have this, but.
Just to kind of fill in
that last one, right?
You could put in the one as
well, so we can be thorough.
And so for this one, right, so
we have our butane and then we
have the, uh, the methyl group.
And it's connected to not the
one position this time, but it's
connected to carbon number two.
So this is where you can see where
the branches actually do matter.
So you can see we have two methoxy.
Uh, butane, and that would
be the name of our molecule.
Let's go through the, some
common naming examples.
So when it comes to common naming, the
whole idea here is that the way that we
picture it is that if we have an ether,
it's like we're labeling the two branches.
So the two alk and aromatic groups, we're
gonna put 'em in alphabetical order.
And then we're just gonna
follow it with the word ether.
Now, with this one, it does,
it is something that is a
very nice naming scheme.
It is very simple.
So like for example, if I'm gonna
cake, kind of do this one, right?
We have methyl on the left,
we have propyl on the right.
So when we write out the entire name
alphabetical M before comes before p.
So it'll be methyl propyl, and then
we're gonna end it with the word ether.
So in this situation, it
would be methyl propyl ether.
Now, being that we're treating the
meats both by as branches, this
thing is not useful all the time.
So not everything has a common name.
I mean, you can try, you
probably can come up with a, with
something for every molecule.
But really the only time that we ever
use in chemistry or organic is when
you have straight chains, uh, cyclic
groups, or maybe even branches, anything
that could be named simply if you start
kind of having all these different
numbered positions and things like that.
It's really not that useful.
So it's something that is when you
have two straight chains, like where
I have a propyl, three carbons in
a row, the methyl one carbon row.
Really easy to write it that way.
Methyl propyl ether.
You don't have to think about it too much.
No.
Um, other ways of doing it.
'cause if we were to go the other way,
right, you would have methoxy propane,
which is a pretty simple name too.
But if you're someone that's more,
that doesn't really know them a lot,
you can kind of just kind of break
it down by the two different pieces.
Whether it's Common or IUPAC.
So let's go through and practice a couple
of the common names just to see how we do.
Okay, so we're gonna do the same thing.
So we're gonna be kind of
counting our two sides.
So I can see I have two carbons
on the right and then I have
three on the on the left.
So we have a ethyl and a propyl.
So ethyl is going to come
first alphabetically.
So it would be ethyl propyl Ether.
Do our combin name.
It's not too bad, right?
It's a little bit quicker.
Okay, so now this one, how do we do this?
This portion.
Now keep in mind, even though this is
a benzene ring, how do you name benzene
as an, um, as an alial group, right?
As an attachment.
So with this one, right, that's where
the phenyl, uh, portion's gonna come
from, which is like one of the general
functional groups that you have as
like one, like reference material.
So we have a phenyl and then a
methyl, so it's gonna be methyl.
Ether.
So in that case, it just helps
you name the two portions.
And then the last one, well,
okay, we do the same thing.
We have our two branches, which
are identical to each other.
So if we were to kind of write them,
it would look like this first, right?
So it'd be ethyl, ethyl, ethyl
Ether, which sounds a little silly.
So what you can do is you can
combine them together just like
you would do for any branch.
So in that case it would
make Dibutyl or not.
Why did I say Dibutyl di Ethyl Ether.
Okay, so Dathyl Ether.
And that's only because
they're the exact same branch.
That's the only time you can do that.
So you can have like di Propyl,
dibutyl , whatever, but it's when
you have two identical branches.
So you can see common
actually can be pretty useful.
Um, just a kinda like quick review, you
know, for the IU pack naming for each
of these two, just to kind of compare.
So let's say if we were to look at,
let's say the first one, so what
would the IUPAC be in this case?
Well, you have eth oxy.
That's a shorter portion, and then it's
gonna be ending with propane, right?
So you can see it's either ethyl,
propyl ether, or oxy propane.
Then the next one, right,
so what's the smaller chain?
So that would be meth, oxy, and then
it's gonna be ended with benzene.
Okay.
And then the last one.
Okay, this is one, like the common name is
way nicer di ethyl ether is really common.
It's easy to say versus the other one,
which would be f oxy ethane, right?
So you're kind of ending with
like the two exact things.
So it's not that one is shorter than
the other or easier than the other.
It's kind of just different situations.
It depends on which one
you really want to use.
Okay.
Well, I hope that this
video helped a little bit.
This is all the examples I have.
Um, good luck studying and let,
please let me know if you have any
questions and I will see you all later.
And this is your first time here.
Hit that like button, subscribe
to the channel for more chemistry
help and more videos to come.
All right, thank you so much and I
hope you all have a wonderful day.
Bye now.